<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Authors | NeuraSYS</title>
    <link>https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/authors/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/authors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Authors</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 21:36:41 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://maddataanalyst.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Authors</title>
      <link>https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/authors/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Filip Wójcik</title>
      <link>https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/authors/filip/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/authors/filip/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name is Filip Wójcik and I’m a data scientist and a programmer with specialization in artificial intelligence and machine learning. Recently I have also become a Ph.D. at the Wroclaw University of Economics, IT in Economics Institute, faculty of Business Intelligence in Management. I’ve also graduated as a lawyer but… well… everybody makes mistakes, so let’s skip this part 🙂&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Machine learning and matters related with data science are my hobby, professional activity and the most important research area. I believe, that I’ve found (so often discussed) balance between those main life areas. Now I try to share my passion with students and all interested people during conferences and lectures. This website was designed to be a platform to share educational materials and my research papers findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from that – I’m a happy husband, keeper of two lovely kittens and sports fanatic – starting from (so popular now) CrossFit, through martial arts (2nd Dan Aikido, self-defense instructor and Krav Maga prcaticioner) ending up with mountains tourism.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
