<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>recommendation systems | NeuraSYS</title>
    <link>https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/tag/recommendation-systems/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/tag/recommendation-systems/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>recommendation systems</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://maddataanalyst.github.io/media/icon_hu5b489458e36ca6f814edb4aedf2e84e5_21223_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>recommendation systems</title>
      <link>https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/tag/recommendation-systems/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning usage as recommendation engine</title>
      <link>https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/project/deep_learning_recommenders/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/project/deep_learning_recommenders/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;project-intro&#34;&gt;Project intro&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to announce the release of software project &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Deep Hybrid Recommenders&amp;rdquo; (DHR)&lt;/strong&gt;, accompanying the paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/345872960_Improvement_of_e-commerce_recommendation_systems_with_deep_hybrid_collaborative_filtering_with_content_A_case_study&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Improvement of e-commerce recommendation systems with deep hybrid collaborative filtering with content: A case study&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; written by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/mgornik&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Michał Górnik&lt;/a&gt; and myself. This project provides Pytorch and PytorchLightning implementations of the discussed algorithms, including Deep Collaborative Filtering (DCF), Collaborative Filtering (CF), and the proposed approach - Deep Hybrid Collaborative Filtering with Content (DHCF).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DHR also includes a repeatable experimentation environment, built using &lt;a href=&#34;https://kedro.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kedro&lt;/a&gt;, which allows for easy experimentation and reproduction of the results from the paper. The experiment was conducted on the 2018 Amazon Reviews Dataset, and evaluated using mean squared error (MSE), mean absolute error (MAE), and mean absolute percentage error (MAPE) metrics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project will be helpful for researchers and practitioners working on product recommendation systems and data scientists seeking existing implementations of recommendation engines based on deep learning. The code is open-source and available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/maddataanalyst/deep-hybrid-recommenders&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;our GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;, and we welcome any feedback or contributions from the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-kedro-processing-pipeline&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;png&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/project/deep_learning_recommenders/kedro_pipeline_hue20e913fc02a688fc018c40fa345014a_202549_83f7e06e4acaf02d3b83a539cf0032db.webp 400w,
               /en/project/deep_learning_recommenders/kedro_pipeline_hue20e913fc02a688fc018c40fa345014a_202549_c3094c4d153cd66f6cdb69d1cd12ff97.webp 760w,
               /en/project/deep_learning_recommenders/kedro_pipeline_hue20e913fc02a688fc018c40fa345014a_202549_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/project/deep_learning_recommenders/kedro_pipeline_hue20e913fc02a688fc018c40fa345014a_202549_83f7e06e4acaf02d3b83a539cf0032db.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;407&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Kedro processing pipeline
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;next-steps&#34;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The future work on Deep Hybrid Recommender will focus primarily on including the graph neural networks as recommendation models, as their usability and applicability to the e-commerce domain have been proven. GNNs for heterogeneous domains (graphs with varied node types) are a relatively new and extensively researched topic with promising results. We will also be working on extending the experimentation environment to include more datasets and models.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Usage of deep neural networks as recommendation engines. Review of selected approaches</title>
      <link>https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/publication/deep_learning_as_recommenders/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 21:36:41 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/publication/deep_learning_as_recommenders/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One concept to rule them all - uses of neural embeddings beyond natural language processing</title>
      <link>https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/talk/one-concept-to-rule-them-all-uses-of-neural-embeddings-beyond-natural-language-processing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/talk/one-concept-to-rule-them-all-uses-of-neural-embeddings-beyond-natural-language-processing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal of this presentation and associated paper is to present results of investigation related to use of the Extreme Gradient Boosting XGBoost algorithm as a forecasting tool. The data provided by the Rossman Com-pany, with a request to design an innovative prediction method, has been used as a base for this case study. The data contains details about micro- and macro-environment, as well as turnover of 1115 stores. Performance of the algorithm was compared to classical forecasting models SARIMAX and Holt-Winters, using time-series cross validation and tests for statistical importance in prediction quality dif-ferences. Metrics of root mean squared percentage error (RMSPE), Theil’s coeffi-cient and adjusted correlation coefficient were analyzed. Results where then passed to Rossman for verification on a separate validation set, via Kaggle.com platform. Study results confirmed, that XGBoost, after using proper data preparation and training method, achieves better results than classical models.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improvement of e-commerce recommendation systems with deep hybrid collaborative filtering with content: A case study</title>
      <link>https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/publication/deep_hybrid_recommendation_system/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2020 21:36:41 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/publication/deep_hybrid_recommendation_system/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recommendation engines based on autoencoders</title>
      <link>https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/talk/recommendation-engines-based-on-autoencoders/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2019 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maddataanalyst.github.io/en/talk/recommendation-engines-based-on-autoencoders/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recommendation engines are probably the most important tools for modern e-commerce organizations. As the data volumes grow larger and larger (as well as product/user base), traditional approaches based on collaborative might be not enough. During this talk I will present alternative approaches to recommendations - making use of deep stacked autoencoders.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
