<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Graph-Neural-Networks on Filip Wójcik</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/graph-neural-networks/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Graph-Neural-Networks on Filip Wójcik</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/graph-neural-networks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>HeXtractor: Automated Heterogeneous Graph Extraction from Multimodal Data</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/research/hextractor_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/research/hextractor_paper/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Transforming diverse data sources into graph representations suitable for deep learning remains a challenge in modern machine learning. HeXtractor provides a standardized, automated framework for converting structured and unstructured data into heterogeneous graphs compatible with Graph Neural Networks (GNNs).&#xA;HeXtractor in action&#xA;Publication and Citation Publication: Journal of Open Source Software, Volume 10, Issue 110, Article 8057, 2025&#xA;Authors: Filip Wójcik, Marcin Malczewski&#xA;Repository: Available on GitHub&#xA;Documentation: HeXtractor Documentation</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MAGIC: Multi-Aggregation Custom Edge GIN for Advanced Money Laundering Detection</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/research/magic_aml/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/research/magic_aml/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Financial crime detection is a challenging application of machine learning due to severe class imbalances and the complexity of transaction networks. This article introduces MAGIC (Multiple Aggregations for Graph Isomorphism Network with Custom Edges), an enhancement of Graph Isomorphism Networks designed to identify illicit financial transactions.&#xA;MAGIC architecture&#xA;Publication and Citation Publication: Journal of Data Science, 2025&#xA;Author: Filip Wójcik&#xA;DOI: https://doi.org/10.6339/25-JDS1190&#xA;Access: View Publication&#xA;Citation: Wójcik, F. (2025). Money Laundering Detection with Multi-Aggregation Custom Edge GIN.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HexGIN: Heterogeneous Graph Isomorphism Networks for Real-World Money Laundering Detection</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/research/hexgin_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/research/hexgin_paper/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This article introduces HexGIN (Heterogeneous extension for Graph Isomorphism Network), an architecture designed to detect money laundering patterns in complex, real-world financial networks. Unlike studies relying on synthetic data, this work evaluates the publicly available FinCEN Files dataset to analyze observed laundering patterns.&#xA;HexGIN architecture&#xA;Publication and Citation Publication: Econometrics. Ekonometria. Advances in Applied Data Analysis, Volume 28, Issue 2, 2024&#xA;Author: Filip Wójcik&#xA;DOI: 10.15611/eada.2024.2.03&#xA;Access: View Publication</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
